2019年1月3日，中国嫦娥4号月球探测器携带玉兔2号月球车在月球背面软着陆
With the surprise landing of a Chinese Rover Yutu 2 or the Jade rabbit 2
and the Chang'e lander on the far side of a Moon on the 3rd of January 2019,
我打算好好统计一下人类在月球上留下了什么东西
I thought it'd be interesting to see what sort of things we've actually put up on the Moon
并推测一下它们将来会怎样
and to speculate on what might happen to them in the future.
阿波罗任务在月球表面上留下了最多的东西，这点是毋庸置疑的
Now it will come as no surprise that the Apollo missions have left behind the most amount of items
但在说到阿波罗任务之前
but long before they were even thought of,
苏联在很久之前就把东西送上月球，美国人不止一次以为苏联做不到
the Soviets pulled off something that not for the first time the U.S. thought they couldn't actually do.
在1959年，苏联的月球2号探测器成为了首个
In 1959 the Soviet Luna 2 probe was the first man-made object
主动撞机月球表面的人造物体
to intentionally impact on to the lunar surface,
而当时美国离月球最近的探测任务是先驱4号
the closest to the US had got to the Moon by then was with a pioneer 4,
而它也只是在六万公里外飞跃月球
but that was 60,000 kilometers away,
这让美国人有点震惊，因为美国人认为
which was a bit of a shock because the U.S. believed that
虽然当时苏联有更大的火箭，但他们导航和制导精度不够
while the Soviets had bigger rockets, they were lacking the precision in their navigation and guidance systems.
虽然这些早期的探测器撞月任务更多的是宣传意义
Although these early probes were designed to crash into the Moon in a piece of pure propaganda,
但月球2号还是留下了一张名片告诉后人他们是先来的
Luna 2 left behind a calling card to remind everyone else that they were here first.
月球2号除了一些实验设备，还带了两个球
Luna 2 was loaded not only with experiments but two small spheres,
一个直径7.5厘米，一个12厘米
one 7.5 cm and the other 12 cm across,
每个上面都印有五边形的苏联国徽
and made from pentagonal pennants, each stamped with the insignia of the Soviet Union,
大球上还印有“1959”
and the date 1959 on the larger of the two.
球体中心有爆炸物，可以在撞击时把国徽散播在月球的土地上
These spheres had an explosive core and were designed to explode and scatter the pennants on impact.
作为第一个到达月球的人造物体，它们后来的命运就不好说了
Although these were the very first man-made items to make it to the Moon their fate is unknown.
因为月球2号当时以每秒3.3公里、每小时12000公里的速度撞击月球
As Luna 2 impacted a speed of around 3.3 km/s about 12,000 kilometers an hour
估计在撞击瞬间就灰飞烟灭了
and was probably vaporized on impact.
第三个球在月球2号的火箭里，发射三十分钟后落回地球
A third sphere was in the Luna 2's rocket body which crashed about 30 minutes later
里面装有液体和一条铝条，上面印有1959年
that was filled with liquid and aluminum strips with the year 1959
第一行：1959年 9月
第二行：苏维埃社会主义共和国联盟
和“苏维埃社会主义共和国联盟”字样
and Union of Soviet Socialist Republics engraved upon them.
随着太空竞赛的加剧，人们对月球的研究也随之进步
As the space race intensified the lunar research also increased.
美国发射了徘徊者号探测器近距离拍摄了月球照片
The U.S. sent the Ranger probes to take close-up images of the Moon.
他们也和苏联一样让探测器撞击月球
They did this like the soviet lunar probes by crashing into the Moon
并在同时向地球实时传输视频信号
whilst transmitting live TV signals back to Earth.
有段时间这个项目被称为“射就完事了”
At one point it was called the "shoot and hope" program
因为九个徘徊者号探测器的前六个有的在发射台炸了(1、2号)
because the first six out of nine range probes either failed on the launch pad,
有的彻底错过月球(3、5号)，有的还没到月球摄像机坏了(6号)
missed the Moon completely or failed before reaching the Moon's surface.
之后美国启动了勘测者计划
This was followed up by the surveyor program
来了解月球表面更多信息，并为阿波罗任务选择潜在的着陆点
to find out more about the actual surface and potential landing sites for Apollo.
当时有人担心着陆到月球的探测器会“沉没”在月尘中
as it was feared by some but any Lander would just sink and disappear into the lunar dust.
七个勘测者号探测器中的五个成功着陆，证明了之前的担忧是多余的
Five out of the seven surveyors successfully landed and proved that theory was groundless.
与此同时，NASA启动月球轨道计划，成为NASA首个环绕勘探月球
Also around this time, the lunar orbiter program was the first NASA craft orbit and survey the Moon
任务包括为阿波罗任务绘制月球重力场地图
including mapping its gravitational field again for the Apollo missions.
在任务完成后，月球轨道探测器离轨，撞击月球
After their missions were complete, the orbiters were deorbited and crashed into the Moon
以保证它们不会威胁阿波罗任务
so they wouldn't pose any threat to the Apollo missions.
美国那边的月球轨道探测器1、2、3号撞击月球背面
With lunar orbiters one, two and three ending up on the far side of the Moon,
在前四次软着陆尝试失败的情况下，苏联这边成功率看着不怎么靠谱
the Soviets had a seemingly hit and miss success rate with the first four attempts of a soft landing failed.
终于在1966年2月3日，月球9号探测器成为人类首个月球软着陆的探测器
Finally on the 3rd Feb 1966 lunar 9 became the first lunar lander to achieve and survive a soft landing.
人们常常忽视的一点是：送飞船上天的火箭也会坠毁月球
Something which is often overlooked is the rockets that carried the spacecraft also ended up on the Moon.
阿波罗11、13到17号的土星五号火箭三级最终都坠毁在月球
The third stage of the Saturn V that carried the Apollo missions 11, 13, 14, 15, 16 and 17 also crashed into the Moon
有些落点还很有名
and some of their positions are well known.
也就是后来的“J002E3”
阿波罗12号的三级本来要去绕日轨道
Apollo 12 third stage was planned to go into a solar orbit
但由于燃料箱排出的燃料让它没有足够剩余燃料
but due to venting of his fuel tanks it didn't have enough propellant
最终三级进入了地月之间的稳定轨道中
and ended up in a stable orbit between the Earth and the Moon.
虽然阿波罗13号没有登月，但它用过的三级也检测到了撞击月球
Even though Apollo 13 never landed, its spent third stage was detected hitting the surface
撞击坑被月球勘测轨道飞行器相机拍到
and the impact crater has been captured by the Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter camera
撞击点位于阿波罗12号着陆点135公里处
some 135 kilometers away from the Apollo 12 site.
阿波罗12号以后的所有任务都在月球留下了阿波罗月球表面实验包
Apollo 12 and all the following missions left behind the ALSEP or Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package.
内含一系列实验仪器，包括用于检测阿波罗13号三级撞击的月震仪
This included a range of experiments like the seismometer which picked up the Apollo 13 third-stage impact
还有其他设备，比如检测微陨石的
as well as other devices through the analysis of micro meteorites,
月球重力、磁场、太阳辐射、大气和内部结构的
the Moon's gravity, magnetic field, solar radiation, atmosphere and internal structure.
阿波罗11号在月球上放置了月球激光测距实验仪
Apollo 11 left behind the lunar laser ranging experiment
它是今天唯一一个仍然可用的实验仪器
which is the only lunar experiment still to be working today
使用地球上的激光就可以测量地月距离
and uses an Earth-based laser to measure the distance from the Earth to the Moon
精度可达3厘米
with an accuracy of about three centimeters.
阿波罗任务中，登月舱整个着陆月球，但没法整个离开
The Apollo missions landed with a complete lander but they couldn't return in the same way,
只有登月舱上升级能带着宇航员起飞离开月球
only the ascent stage of the lander took off to return the crew
且有着非常严格的重量限制，超重可能就没法飞回指令舱了
and they had a very strict weight limits, too much weight and they might not make it back to the command module
真正意义上的差一公斤都不行
literally every kilogram made a difference,
这也是为啥会留下一堆看似随机的物品清单，我们稍后会看到该清单
and that was a reason for leaving behind the seemingly random list of objects as we will see later.
当宇航员从登月舱上升级回到指令舱
Once the crews had transferred from the ascent module to the command module,
上升级会再次分离并坠毁在月球，除了两个例外
the ascent modules were released to crash back onto the lunar surface except 2.
阿波罗13号登月舱变成宇航员返回地球的“救生艇”
Apollo 13 which was used as a lifeboat to get the crew back to Earth
最终在地球大气中烧毁，另一个例外是阿波罗10号
and burned up in the Earth's atmosphere and Apollo 10.
阿波罗10号是阿波罗11号除着陆以外的完整彩排
Apollo 10 was a complete dress rehearsal for Apollo 11 except for the landing.
尤金·塞尔南和托马斯·斯塔福德驾驶登月舱到月球表面15公里高处后返回
Eugene Cernan and Thomas Stafford took the lunar lander to within 15 kilometers of the surface before returning.
实际上那次任务里上升级故意少装了燃料，防止宇航员尝试登陆月球
In fact the ascent stage was deliberately short fueled to stop the crew from attempting a landing on the Moon
因为那样的话他们就没有足够燃料回到指令舱了
because if they did they wouldn't have enough fuel to make it back to the command module.
阿波罗10号登月舱下降级留在了轨道，没有坠毁月球，位置未知
The Apollo 10 descent stage was left in orbit but fell back to the Moon and it's position is unknown.
在宇航员离开“史努比”号登月舱后
After the crew had transferred the ascent stage nicknamed "Snoopy",
他们点燃了登月舱的发动机使其耗尽燃料
fired its engine until it ran out of fuel.
这一操作让它进入了绕日轨道并至今仍在那条轨道上
This sent it out into an orbit around the Sun, and it's still there,
在一条比地球略小的绕日轨道的某个位置上
somewhere, in an orbit slightly shorter than that of the Earth,
它也成为唯一一个曾经载人并留在太空的飞船
the only manned spacecraft left in space without a crew.
如果你看每次任务留在月球的东西列表
If you look at the inventory of items left behind for each mission
视频说明有该清单下载链接
你能看到一大堆相当普通的东西
you'll see a lot of really rather mundane items.
比如过滤器、尿液、粪便袋、食物包、座椅扶手、毛巾
Things like filters, urine and defecation bags, food bags, chair arm rests, towels,
电池、耳塞、牙刷、靴子、钳子、工具、秤，超过八百个
batteries, earplugs, brushes, boots, tongs, tools, scales in fact over eight hundred items.
NASA专门列了一份22页的清单记录留在月球的东西
NASA has created a 22-page-document listing everything on the Moon
你可以下载下来细细查看
which you can download and peruse for yourself.
还有些东西你可能以为他们本该带回来
But there are also some things that you think they would like to bring back
比如每个平均拍1500张照片的哈苏相机
like the Hasselblad cameras which were used to take on average 1500 photos each
但阿波罗任务使用的14个中有12个被留在月球
but no they left behind 12 of the 14 taken on the Apollo missions.
宇航员按照指示，只带回了胶卷盒
The astronauts were instructed to bring back just the film canisters
而不带回相机，从而为月球岩石样本留下空间
and leave the cameras to make room for rock samples.
这使得六次任务可以多带回25千克的岩石
This allowed an extra 25 kilograms of rocks to be brought back over six missions in place of the cameras.
当然，有些东西太大了带不回去
Of course some things were just far too big to bring back
比如三个月球车和上面的摄影机
like the three lunar Rovers along with their TV cameras.
它们留在月球表面，由地球远程操控拍摄宇航员从月球起飞的画面
They were left behind to film the ascent from a Moon by remote control on Earth.
还有一个镀金的望远镜
There was also a gold-plated telescope,
唯一一个地球以外的星球表面观测太空的望远镜
the only one to make observations from a surface of a celestial body other than the Earth.
还有一些象征性的东西，通常不是官方批准的东西
Other things left behind were symbolic in nature and were not always officially sanctioned.
阿波罗11号除了国旗，还留下了一个黄金橄榄枝以表示和平
We all know the U.S. flags but Apollo 11 also left behind a gold olive branch as a representation of peace.
还留下了阿波罗1号的徽章，纪念死于训练中火灾的三位宇航员
An Apollo 1 patch to honor the crew of Grissom, White and Chaffey who died in a fire during testing,
还有纪念已去世的宇航员加加林和科马洛夫的奖牌
and medals given to the families of the deceased cosmonauts Gagarin and Komarov.
还有一个月球纪念盘
There is also the Moon memorial disc
上面有艾森豪威尔、肯尼迪、约翰逊、尼克松总统的友好致辞
which contained the goodwill statements by President Eisenhower, Kennedy, Johnson and Nixon
还有当时世界上73个国家领导人的致辞
and messages from the leaders of 73 countries from around the world.
盘片制作技术类似早期的集成电路
The disc was made using the same techniques as early integrated circuits
大小和50美分硬币差不多，用显微镜可以看到书写内容
and is the size of a U.S. 50-cent coin with the writing visible using a microscope.
阿波罗15号中留下了一个称为“倒下的宇航员”的9厘米雕塑和一个石碑
On Apollo 15 a nine centimeter statue called "Fallen Astronaut" along with a plaque
以此纪念14名苏联和美国在航天飞行或训练过程中牺牲的宇航员
commemorating the 14 US and Soviet astronauts which died during training
并由宇航员大卫·斯科特非正式地放在了月球表面
was unofficially placed on the Moon by David Scott.
在阿波罗16号任务中，查尔斯·杜克将他和妻子、两个女儿的照片留在月球
And on Apollo 16 Charlie Duke left a photo of himself his wife and two children on the surface.
照片背面写道
On the back he wrote
“这是在1972年4月20日登陆月球的，
来自地球的宇航员查尔斯·杜克的全家”
在阿波罗任务期间与之后
During and after the Apollo missions,
苏联在1970-1973年间仍在进行可远程控制的月球步行者1、2号任务
the Soviets continued with their remote-controlled lunokhod Rovers 1 and 2 in 1970 and 1973.
月球步行者2号运行4个月，行进42公里，传回86张全景照片和八万张照片
Lunokhod 2 operated for four months traveling 42 kilometers and sending back 86 panoramicimages and 80,000 TV pictures.
从那以后就只有来自美国、日本、印度和中国的卫星了
Since then there have only been satellites from the US, Japan, India and China
它们多数是最终坠毁在月球表面
most of which have ended up on the surface,
直到2013年12月，中国的嫦娥3号和玉兔号使之成为世界第三个
until December 2013 when the Chinese became only the third country
成功进行月球软着陆的国家
原视频口误说成嫦娥四号，实际上指的是嫦娥三号
to soft land on the Moon with the Chang'e 3 and the Yutu or Jade rabbit Rover.
虽然月球车两个月后因为月尘导致的机械故障无法工作
Although the rover succumbed to a mechanical abnormality probably caused by the lunar dust after two months,
但着陆器本身自带放射性同位素热电机与太阳能电池
the lander which is powered by radioisotope thermoelectric generator and solar cells
使其着陆四年半后与地面控制中心有联系
was still in contact with the ground control some four and a half years after it landed,
并且它的能源理论上仍能坚持30年
and in theory its power supply could last for 30 years.
那么月球上这些东西结局会如何？
So what will happen to the things left on the Moon.
有些人说月球没有各种侵蚀作用、风化、雨水或者火山活动
Some say that with no erosion, no wind, rain or volcanic activity,
它们活的会比人类还长
they will be there long after the human race has come to an end
未来上百万甚至数十亿年不变，但他们忽略了几个问题
in the millions or even billions of years into the future, but they are forgetting a few things.
首先是月尘，月尘覆盖整个月球表面，且仍在因陨石撞击而生成
Firstly the lunar dust, it covers the entire Moon and was created and still is being created by meteor impact.
虽然月球上没有吹动它们的风
Although there is no wind to move it around,
但它们会因太阳紫外、X波段辐射而带电
it becomes electrostatically charged from the Sun's ultraviolet and x-ray radiation.
导致其漂浮空中，形成极其稀薄的月尘大气
This causes it to levitate and create a very thin atmosphere of dust,
持续随着月球昼夜交替在晨昏线附近升起落下
constantly rising and falling around the terminator line as it sweeps across the surface from lunar day to lunar night.
最近的研究实验表明月尘积累速度大约是每千年一毫米
Recent observations and experiments show that the dust builds up at a rate of around about one millimeter per thousand years.
听上去挺慢的，但在一百万年内
Now that sounds like a tiny amount but in a million years,
月球上所有东西都会掩埋在一米的月尘下方
all the items on the Moon would be under a meter of dust,
这只是假设我们什么都不做防止情况恶化的前提下
and that's assuming we didn't do anything to make it worse.
如果我们未来在月球采矿，扬起的月尘会越来越多
If we start mining on the Moon then the amount of dust raised will be much much more,
借助六分之一的重力与无空气阻力的环境，它们能飘非常的远
and with only one-sixth gravity and no air resistance it could also travel a very long way.
另一个因素是太阳，月球没有地球那样保护自身的大气层
Then there is the Sun, with no protective atmosphere like the Earth,
表面所有东西都完全暴露在太阳的紫外、X波段射线和带电粒子下
anything on the surface is exposed to the full force of the Sun's ultraviolet, x-ray and ionizing charged particles
想想那些被太阳暴晒的照片和涂料的下场就知道了
just look at its effect here on Earth on paint pigments and photos that have been left out in the Sun.
没有大气的另一个问题是温度
That lack of atmosphere also means there is almost no temperature regulation
太阳直射月球温度可达到127°C，晚上则能下降到-173°C
so in direct sunlight the surface can reach a 127 °C and at night it can drop to minus 173 °C.
这上下三百摄氏度的温差就够月表那些东西喝一壶的了
The thermal stress of that 300 degree temperature range would also take its toll on anything left there.
查尔斯·杜克47年前留下的照片估计早就完全褪色了
The photo that Charlie Duke left 47 years ago is probably completely bleached by now
那些美国国旗和各种涂料的表面最终下场也差不多
as are the U.S. flags and pigments and painted surfaces will have degraded
还有一个因素是微陨石直接撞击或落在附近
and is also the sandblasting effect of micro meteorites hitting objects directly or nearby
仍然会激起烦人的月尘
and lunar dust which is highly abrasive.
所以虽然相比放在地球，它们在月球表面可能活时间更长一点
So while they may well in some ways last a lot longer than they would do compared to being left outside on Earth,
但最终也逃不过相同的、化为尘埃的命运
they will meet the same fate and eventually crumble to dust.
阿波罗留在月球那么多东西的原因之一
One of the reasons for Apollo leaving so much stuff on the Moon
是他们可以带回登月舱上升级的重量是有限的
was the limited weight they could carry back in the ascent module.
要榨干每一千克的运力，他们就得决定什么留下什么带走
With every kilogram making a difference they had to choose what to bring back and what to leave.
这只是登月计划中无数困难的冰山一角
These were just some of the myriad of problems that had to be solved
相比于整个任务，这些琐事关注度并不那么高
often with very short notice on the missions themselves
这不止是对于阿波罗任务，每个月球相关的任务都是这样
not only for Apollo but for every lunar mission that's ever been attempted.
字幕翻译给虫，欢迎点赞投币收藏分享转发评论关注充电~
接下来是原视频广告时间
If you like to challenge yourself
then our sponsor for this video brilliant.org has something that will be right up your street.
Brilliant's daily problems provide you with a challenge
and then the context and framework you need to work them out,
so that you learn the concepts by applying them.
If you like the daily problem
then there are more like it so you can explore the concept in greater detail and develop your framework.
If you're confused and need more guidance then join the community in discussing these problems.
These thought-provoking challenges will lead you from curiosity to mastery one day at a time.
So what are you waiting for go to brilliant.org/CuriousDroid and finish your day a little smarter.
And the first 200 of you to do so will also get 20% off of the annual subscription
and be able to view all the problems in the archives.